Exercise 1-54, shifting your voice position. You should feel a high vibration
in your nasal passages as well as in your fingers. Now continue holding your nose
and completely relax your throat. Allow an ah sound to flow from deep in your chest.
Ah. There should be no vibration in your nose at all. Go back and forth several
times. Ah, ah, ah, ah. Next, we practice flowing from one position to the other so
you can feel exactly when it changes from a nasal sound to a deep, rich schwa.
Remember how it was imitating a man's voice when you were little? Do that, pinch
your nose, and repeat after me. Ah, ah, ah, ah. Here, we'll practice the same
progression, sound.
There are three nasal consonants, M, N, and NG. These have non-nasal counterparts,
M and B, N and D, NG and G. We're going to practice totally denasalizing your voice
for a moment, which means turning the nasals into the other consonants. We'll
read the same sentence three times. The first will be quite nasal. The second will
sound like you have a cold. The third will have appropriate nasal consonants but
denasalized vowels. Repeat after me. Mary might need money. Mary might need money.
Mary might need money.